<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>GAN on Alexey Borsky</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/tags/gan/</link><description>Recent content in GAN on Alexey Borsky</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://volotat.github.io/tags/gan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>ConGAN</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/projects/2018-01-29-congan/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://volotat.github.io/projects/2018-01-29-congan/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://volotat.github.io/projects/2018-01-29-congan/faces_table.png" alt="Featured image of post ConGAN" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continuous Adversarial Image Generator that can produce high-quality images with relatively few examples and resolution independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project implements a Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) that learns a continuous function mapping coordinates (x, y) and a latent vector z to an RGB color, rather than generating a fixed grid of pixels. By treating images as continuous functions, the model creates a &amp;ldquo;vector-like&amp;rdquo; representation that can be sampled at any resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The architecture differs from traditional GANs by using a coordinate-based generator. The system includes an &amp;ldquo;Ident&amp;rdquo; network to map images to a latent space, a Generator that predicts colors based on position and latent codes, and a Discriminator that validates pixel data in context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results demonstrated that the model could generalize well from small datasets (10-20 images is enough for reasonable results, while training the network completely from the scratch) and produce smooth interpolations in the latent space, effectively hallucinating plausible variations between training examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Completed Experiment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/volotat/ConGAN" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;View on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>