<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Digital Immortality on Alexey Borsky</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/tags/digital-immortality/</link><description>Recent content in Digital Immortality on Alexey Borsky</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://volotat.github.io/tags/digital-immortality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Anagnorisis. Part 3: Why Should You Go Local?</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/p/anagnorisis-part-3-why-should-you-go-local/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://volotat.github.io/p/anagnorisis-part-3-why-should-you-go-local/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://volotat.github.io/p/anagnorisis-part-3-why-should-you-go-local/External-Hard-Drive-Hero.png" alt="Featured image of post Anagnorisis. Part 3: Why Should You Go Local?" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;rsquo;s digital age, an increasing amount of personal data is stored on cloud services, often beyond our direct control. While these platforms offer convenience, they also pose significant risks regarding data ownership, privacy, and longevity. Recent incidents, such as the cyberattacks on the &lt;a class="link" href="https://web.archive.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;, highlight the vulnerability of digital repositories. In October 2024, the Internet Archive suffered a data breach that &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.wired.com/story/internet-archive-hacked/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;exposed&lt;/a&gt; information from over 31 million user accounts. This breach was accompanied by DDoS attacks, leading to intermittent service &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/10/14/24269741/internet-archive-online-read-only-data-breach-outage" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;disruptions&lt;/a&gt;. Furthermore in March 2023, a U.S. District Court ruled that the Internet Archive&amp;rsquo;s practice of lending digitized books online constituted copyright infringement, leading to a permanent &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hachette_v._Internet_Archive" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;injunction&lt;/a&gt; against such activities. These events underscore how external factors can &lt;a class="link" href="https://brownstone.org/articles/they-are-scrubbing-the-internet-right-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;jeopardize&lt;/a&gt; access to information stored online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, data loss from cloud services is not uncommon. Service outages, cyberattacks, and policy changes can result in the sudden unavailability of personal data. For instance, breaches targeting cloud storage providers have exposed sensitive user information, emphasizing the precarious nature of entrusting data to third-party platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An external hard drive could provide up to &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/12/18/24324143/seagate-32tb-hamr-hard-drive" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;32TB of storage&lt;/a&gt; as of january 2025&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="your-data-as-a-reflection-of-your-personality"&gt;Your Data as a Reflection of Your Personality
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every digital interaction we engage in - be it social media activity, spending habits, or smartphone usage - leaves behind a &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.psychologicalscience.org/news/releases/spending-data-personality.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;footprint&lt;/a&gt; that mirrors aspects of our personality. Similarly, patterns in smartphone usage &lt;a class="link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36738137/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;have been linked&lt;/a&gt; to the Big Five personality traits, providing insights into an individual&amp;rsquo;s behavior and preferences.
These digital traces are not just passive records, they actively contribute to the construction of our digital personas. Machine learning algorithms can analyze this data to &lt;a class="link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38753373/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;predict personality traits&lt;/a&gt;, highlighting the intimate connection between our data and our identities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-case-for-localstorage"&gt;The Case for Local Storage
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mitigate these risks, transitioning to local storage solutions is a prudent strategy. By maintaining data on personal devices or dedicated local servers, individuals retain full control over their information, ensuring accessibility regardless of external circumstances. This approach not only safeguards against unforeseen disruptions but also enhances privacy and data security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the need for accessible local storage management, the &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/volotat/Anagnorisis" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Anagnorisis&lt;/a&gt; project is developing as a way to assist users in organizing and preserving their data effectively. The idea behind Anagnorisis is to offer a set of tools that facilitate migration from cloud services such as Notion, Spotify, Pinterest or Youtube to local environments, allowing users to easily find, rate and enjoy their data just as effectively as with any of these services. By providing a user-friendly interface and AI-powered features, Anagnorisis ensures that personal data remains under the user&amp;rsquo;s control, protected from external threats and accessible for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="digital-immortality-through-data-preservation"&gt;Digital Immortality Through Data Preservation
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;While preserving the human mind in its entirety remains beyond current technological capabilities, each piece of data we create serves as a fragment of our identity. By conscientiously preserving this data, we offer future generations the opportunity to reconstruct a digital approximation of our personalities. This form of digital immortality is attainable today, allowing us to leave behind a legacy that extends beyond our physical existence. The ghost of our past self that can support our descendants way beyond our physical death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, by engaging in this conscious attempt to preserve our personality, we may begin to treat our data differently. Instead of hoarding vast amounts of trivial, mostly situational information, that happened to be stored on our SSD and hard drives, we might prioritize storing only the most important and meaningful parts of it. This approach encourages us to reflect on the value of our contributions and fosters a more intentional interaction with our digital environment. Writing down our thoughts more frequently - perhaps not for others to read but as a way to create more data points. These records can serve as the basis for training future machine learning models, creating digital constructs that closely resemble our true selves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-theend"&gt;In the end
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;While cloud services offer undeniable convenience, the potential risks associated with relinquishing control over personal data cannot be overlooked. Embracing local storage solutions, supported by tools like Anagnorisis, provides a secure and reliable alternative, preserving the integrity and accessibility of our digital lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github: &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/volotat/Anagnorisis" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://github.com/volotat/Anagnorisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>