<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Generative Art on Alexey Borsky</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/tags/generative-art/</link><description>Recent content in Generative Art on Alexey Borsky</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://volotat.github.io/tags/generative-art/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Generative Art Synthesizer</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/projects/2021-12-04-generative-art-synthesizer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://volotat.github.io/projects/2021-12-04-generative-art-synthesizer/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://volotat.github.io/projects/2021-12-04-generative-art-synthesizer/gas_preview.png" alt="Featured image of post Generative Art Synthesizer" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Python program that generates Python programs that generate generative art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most generative art relies on stochastic processes where the initial seed and specific parameters are often lost, making exact reproduction difficult. GAS takes a different approach: instead of storing just the output or the parameters, it generates a fully deterministic, standalone Python script for each artwork. This ensures complete reproducibility—if you have the script, you have the art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core mechanism involves initializing a tensor with coordinate data and then applying a random sequence of mathematical transformations (like &lt;code&gt;transit&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;sin&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;magnitude&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;shift&lt;/code&gt;) to its channels. These operations are restricted to the [-1, 1] range to ensure stability. The final result is a composition of these channels converted into color space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-Contained Art:&lt;/strong&gt; Each generated piece is a runnable Python script with zero external dependencies beyond standard scientific libraries (numpy, PIL).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deterministic:&lt;/strong&gt; The generated scripts contain no random elements; running the same script always produces the exact same image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Method-Based generation:&lt;/strong&gt; Uses a palette of composable mathematical functions (&lt;code&gt;sin&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;prod&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;soft_min&lt;/code&gt;, etc.) to &amp;ldquo;sculpt&amp;rdquo; the image in a high-dimensional channel space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aesthetic Scoring:&lt;/strong&gt; Includes a simple scoring model to estimate the visual quality of generated outputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Completed Experiment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/volotat/GAS" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;View on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>