<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ARC-AGI on Alexey Borsky</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/tags/arc-agi/</link><description>Recent content in ARC-AGI on Alexey Borsky</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://volotat.github.io/tags/arc-agi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>NeuroGrammer — a proposal of an architecture for solving the ARC challenge.</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: this text is prepared for readers who already familiar with the ARC challenge. If you don’t know what it is, you can take a look at &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/fchollet/ARC" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;the github page of the challenge&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="link" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01547" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;the original paper “On the Measure of Intelligence”&lt;/a&gt; by François Chollet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main idea is to produce a system that consists of two differentiable parts — a programmer and a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part of the system — programmer — takes three inputs: an input data that should be processed, an output data that should be generated and the current state of the program that supposed to covent an input data into an output data. The task of the programmer is to generate a better version of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_PIA7-UG3vs5eDFc4_Uu0rg.png"
width="376"
height="506"
srcset="https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_PIA7-UG3vs5eDFc4_Uu0rg_hu_4775938ab673f87d.png 480w, https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_PIA7-UG3vs5eDFc4_Uu0rg_hu_170ff55f17f7ba9.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="74"
data-flex-basis="178px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part of the system — computer — takes two inputs: an input data and the program. The task of the computer is to apply the program to the input data and produce an output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_juw57YNOwhc9IWZcFOkggQ.png"
width="378"
height="503"
srcset="https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_juw57YNOwhc9IWZcFOkggQ_hu_65a9b49d2b6e233f.png 480w, https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_juw57YNOwhc9IWZcFOkggQ_hu_6f1f8b8286247e0e.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="75"
data-flex-basis="180px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In actuality the programmer and the computer are both the neural networks and the program is a N-dimensional vector. Because both of the parts are differentiable we could backpropagate through the whole system to train both programmer and computer to work coherently. Furthermore we may propagate through several steps of the pipeline to get better results. With this architecture we could have a system that may take an arbitrary number of examples and produce a solution to a new input based on the program it comes up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test this idea I created a small dataset resembling the ARC, that was partially created by hand and partially generated on the fly, but with some additional restrictions: all tasks have 6x6 grids, each cell has only two states (black and white), all tasks have exactly 5 examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a little glimpse of how the network performed on the tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_D8LE7ETBIURSQyBYaEUl9g.png"
width="2400"
height="410"
srcset="https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_D8LE7ETBIURSQyBYaEUl9g_hu_a8a43799b06fa8a2.png 480w, https://volotat.github.io/p/neurogrammer-architecture-arc-challenge/1_D8LE7ETBIURSQyBYaEUl9g_hu_4f4c9f24c6bcbffe.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="585"
data-flex-basis="1404px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each column (3x6) here represent one task. Inside the task first colum represent an input, second — an output and the third — a guess of the networks considering all previous examples and current input given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experiments this system worked really well for procedurally generated tasks, a bit worse on the in distribution data and horrible on the out of distribution data. In other words, it could solve the type of tasks it saw, but almost always failed on novel ones. Although the scale of the experiments was miniscule and all networks were composed of several fully-connected layers, so there are still a potential to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The ARC Game</title><link>https://volotat.github.io/projects/2021-07-26-the-arc-game/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://volotat.github.io/projects/2021-07-26-the-arc-game/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://volotat.github.io/projects/2021-07-26-the-arc-game/level_example.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The ARC Game" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Abstraction and Reasoning Corpus made into a web game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to create an easy-to-use interface for François Chollet&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/fchollet/ARC-AGI" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Abstraction and Reasoning Corpus (ARC-AGI)&lt;/a&gt;, designed so that children as young as three years old can play with it. This tool explores the potential of using ARC as educational material for developing abstraction and reasoning skills in young kids, challenging cognitive abilities such as pattern recognition, logical reasoning, and problem-solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game presents visual tasks consisting of grid pairs that represent a transformation (input → output). The player must deduce the transformation rule from the examples and apply it to a test grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Child-Friendly Interface:&lt;/strong&gt; Simplified controls allow for painting, dragging to fill, and copying grids, making it accessible for early childhood development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fixed Grid Sizes:&lt;/strong&gt; Unlike the original ARC where output size is part of the solution, here the output grid size is pre-set to reduce complexity and focus on the transformation logic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Printable Version:&lt;/strong&gt; Tasks can be automatically formatted and printed on paper with adjusted colors (e.g., swapping black for white) for offline solving with markers or pencils.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Not Maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="cited-in-scientific-literature"&gt;Cited in Scientific Literature
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://pub.tik.ee.ethz.ch/students/2021-HS/BA-2021-38.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Abstraction and Reasoning Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11793" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Reasoning Abilities of Large Language Models: In-Depth Analysis on the Abstraction and Reasoning Corpus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07866" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;System 2 Reasoning for Human-AI Alignment: Generality and Adaptivity via ARC-AG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3711896.3736831" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Addressing and Visualizing Misalignments in Human Task-Solving Trajectories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://volotat.github.io/ARC-Game/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Play the Game&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/volotat/ARC-Game" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;View on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>